Darren Atherton

Email: darren.a.atherton@gmail.com

GitHub: https://github.com/DarrenAtherton49
Website: http://darrenatherton.co.uk
LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/darrenatherton
Twitter: https://twitter.com/DarrenAtherton

A motivated, goal-driven Android and Kotlin developer with a strong academic background and many years of Android experience. I am passionate about building apps with an excellent user experience, grounded in clean, well-architected and testable code whilst staying up-to-date with the latest developments in open-source Android software and the Android community. I am currently interested in advancing Android development through the use of Kotlin.

Skills

- Android Framework/Studio, Java, Kotlin, clean architecture/SOLID principles, modern design patterns
 (MVP/MVVM/Redux), test-driven development (UI and unit testing), reactive programming (RxJava),
 dependency injection, material design, XML layout design, Gradle build process, continuous integration,
 performance profiling and optimisation (e.g. monitor, Traceview, hierarchy viewer and XML layout
 analysis), JSON/XML parsing, API consumption and Google Play store submission process.
- Libraries/technologies used Support/design libraries, AppCompat, Retrofit 2/OkHttp, RxJava/ RxAndroid, Dagger 2, LeakCanary, Glide/Picasso, Butterknife, Anko, Espresso and Appium (UI testing), JUnit (Domain/Data testing), Mockito, PowerMock, Hamcrest, NexPlayer, ExoPlayer, Timber, FindBugs-IDEA, JSON (Gson), XML, Firebase and SQLite.

Workflow/Process

Git/GitHub, Slack, Jenkins, Jira, Trello, Vysor.

General

- Experienced in working independently and as part of various-sized teams.
- Experienced in troubleshooting and problem-solving.
- Excellent time-management skills developed during the organisation of my own working hours during PhD study.
- Full UK driving license.

Work Experience

Android Developer at Sky

- Sept 2016 Present
- As an Android developer at Sky, I am currently responsible for developing various native applications such as Sky Cinema and Sky+. Sky Cinema enables users to stream both linear and on-demand movies, while Sky+ allows users to interact with their set-top boxes (e.g. to record/manage content or use the app as a TV remote). My core responsibilities include developing the applications, writing unit and UI tests and providing estimates for future work. I also take part in various Android-focused team activities such as organising internal Android meetings and discussing new Android developments with the internal community.
- Android Developer at Eagle Eye Solutions

Nov 2015 - Sept 2016

• Eagle Eye is a SaaS platform that validates and redeems digital promotions in real-time for the grocery, retail and hospitality industries. As an Android developer, I was responsible for developing the native Android white label application which facilitates the redemption of promotions, offers and rewards by interacting with the platform. The applications I developed during this time include Toby Carvery, Green Card Pubs, Nicholson's, All Bar One and Harvester.

Software Engineer at Momote (MyMobileWorkers)

- Jul 2013 Aug 2014
- MyMobileWorkers provides off-the-shelf mobile workforce management software offering features such as field service management, proof of delivery support and asset tracking. As a software Engineer for MyMobileWorkers, I was responsible for working on both the Android application and the web and mobile APIs.
- Lab Demonstrator (Computer Science) at University of Liverpool

Oct 2014 - July 2015

• Modules taught: COMP282 (Advanced Object-Oriented C Languages) and COMP102 (Introduction to Databases). This role involved giving practical code demonstrations to students and assisting them with their lab solutions, as well as marking formal code submissions and giving feedback. The lab classes undertaken involved teaching MySQL, Objective-C and C++.

Education

• PhD Computer Science, University of Liverpool

2014 - 2015

- Status: Withdrawn from studies with 1 year completed successfully.
- Work undertaken: 'Combining Persuasive Technology and Motivation Theories for Children's Language Development'. This project combined notions from artificial intelligence, persuasive technology and behaviour change/motivation theories to develop dynamic, intelligent motivational applications for the purpose of motivating parents to help their young children acquire language. During this time, I undertook this research as a member of the Agent ART research group and in the context of the International Centre for Language and Communicative Development (LuCiD). During this project, I gained a great amount of knowledge on argument and computation theory, artificial intelligence, user modelling, persuasive/motivational technologies, behavioural theory and application interaction design. During this project I also gained important writing and communication skills, by submitting research material to peer-reviewed publication venues and giving corresponding presentations.
- BSc Computer Information Systems, University of Liverpool

2010 - 2013

- Award: First-class honours.
- Notable modules: Programming in Java (84%), Mobile Computing iOS (90%), Group Software Project (80%), Software Development Tools (87%), Multi-Agent Systems (90%), Technologies for E-Commerce (95%) and Experimental Methods in Computing (87%).
- Dissertation: 'A Motivational Interface to a Personalised Tool to Monitor Children's Language Development'. An application which allowed parents to track their child's language development and milestones on a customisable timeline, implemented natively on iOS with Objective-C in Xcode.
- BTEC National Diploma for IT Practitioners, Liverpool Community College

2008 - 2010

- Award: Distinction, Distinction, Distinction.
- GCSE, Halewood College

2002 - 2007

• Award: 9 GCSE's graded A-C, including Mathematics and English.

Awards and Activities

- Awarded an attainment Scholarship each year for continuous achievement throughout my undergraduate degree Department of Computer Science, University of Liverpool (2010 11, 2011 12, 2012 13).
- Awarded a EPSRC Doctoral Training Studentship for the duration of my PhD Department of Computer Science, University of Liverpool (2014 2015).
- Published a two-page abstract and gave a corresponding talk on 'Personalising Motivation: Combining Motivation Theories and Persuasive Technology for Children's Language Development' - Doctoral Consortium, Persuasive Conference 2015, Chicago, Illinois.
- Contributing to open-source software and taking part in discussions on new developments in Android and Kotlin.